Motivation letter

I hereby apply for the positions of Projektmitarbeiter/-in, Kennziffer 71/20107.

I am fluently using R and shiny to do my statistics, which allow reproducibility of the analysis (once new data is fed, only one click allow for a re-run of the analysis) and a good user experience (browser based interface), you might have a look at https://colomb.shinyapps.io/Flystockcleaner/ to get an idea. Moving to jasperstudio, if necessary, should be easy.

I have been working at the university for years, as a research and teaching assistant. I am looking for a part time position, since it would allow me to continue my voluntary work in projects like the open science mooc and the march for science.

I am looking forward to meet you in person, Dr. Julien Colomb

Links:

March for science, orga team: http://marchforscienceberlin.de/wer-wir-sind Scientific achievements: http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3127-5520

Referees:

Prof. Bjoern Brembs, bjoern@brembs.net

Curriculum Vitae

Julien COLOMB, PhD in Biology Schillerpromenade 4 12049 Berlin julien.colomb@fu-berlin.de

https://github.com/jcolomb

http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3127-5520

Birth: 9 April 1979 in Sion (CH) Married, two children

Swiss



Summary

After 12 years spent on fundamental research (neuro-genetics) in which I gathered skills in experimental design, team leading and student teaching, I got most interested in open science and research reproducibility as well as the digital tools helping scientists to achieve it. I would like to apply these novel knowledge while doing research and mentoring students.

Research activities

2017 - present	Postdoctoral fellow, HU (Berlin, Germany), by Prof. Y. Winter
2015 - 2016	Analysing mulitdimensional dataset: the homecagescan case. Postdoctoral fellow, HU & Charité (Berlin , Germany), by Prof. Y. Winter
2014 - 2015	Animal core facility director and project manager. Postdoctoral fellow, HU & Charite (Berlin , Germany), by Prof. Y. Winter
2009 -2013	working on Phenobase. Postdoctoral fellow, FU (Berlin , Germany), by Prof. B. Brembs
2007-2008	working on "the what and where of operant learning in <i>Drosophila</i> ". Postdoctoral fellow, ESPCI (Paris , France), by Dr. T. Preat
	working on "appetitive learning in <i>Drosophila</i> ".

Commercial activities

2016-present Freelance scientist,

Animal core facility (Charité): organisation lead, data analysis in R, Phenobase

(Exist, HU): literature curation.

2012-present Founder and CEO of Drososhare GmbH (Berlin, Germany), facilitating fruit fly

transactions between scientists

Education

2016	FELASA B. HU Berlin
2013	Moderation & management (Continuing Education), FU Berlin/Artop.
2006	PhD in Biology, University of Fribourg (Fribourg, Switzerland).

PhD dissertation: "The chemosensory system of Drosophila larvae: neu-

roanatomy and behaviour" Thesis director: Prof. R.F Stocker

2002 Diploma in Biology, University of Fribourg (Fribourg, Switzerland)

1998 "Maturité fédérale type C" (scientific subsection), in the "Collège de la royale

Abbaye de St. Maurice"

Languages

French (mother tongue), English (fluent), German (fluent), Spanish (basics).

Research output

8 research papers (7 first author), 3 reviews, 1 Scienceopen collection, 3 Open source software (2 main author), Meeting Presentations > 25

https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3127-5520

https://github.com/jcolomb

Supervision of student

2010-2014 Co-supervisor of the PhD student Christine Damrau (with Dr. B.Brembs) on

the role of octopamine in reward, motivation and motor control in *Drosophila*.

2008 Co-supervisor of the PhD student Séverine Trannoy (with Dr. G. Isabel and

Dr. N. Gervasi) on the role of dopamine in appetitive learning consolidation in

Drosophila.

2005 Co-supervisor of the diploma work of Claire Huguenin (with Dr. A. Ramaekers)

on the role of NO in olfactory discrimination in *Drosophila* larvae.

Teaching experience

2016 A	nimal models of neuropathy, (master student, 2x2h lecture, organisation)
2012 G	Genetik (bachelor student, 2 x 3 h. lecture, 2x 1h. seminar)
2012 N	Jeurogenetik. (master student, 2 x 2 h. lecture, 2x 1h. seminar)
2011 P	ractical course neurobiology. (7 x 4 h., Practical course supervision)
2011 E	Intwicklung der Insekten [Insect development] (2 h. lecture)
2006 F	luorescence and Confocal Microscopy (master student, 3h. lecture)
2003-2006 S	tudying behavior. (master student, 2 h. lecture)
2003-2005 D	Developmental- and Neurogenetics (master student, 2 h. lecture).

Computer skills

Organisation: Outlook, Access, labfolder; Publishing: LATEX, Office; html, figshare; Image processing: Photoshop, Illustrator, Image J; Programming and data analysis: R, Rmarkdown, shiny, Git, Labview

Other tasks

Organisation of the Berlin Open Science meetup:

Part of the march for science Berlin Orga team:

Creation of the T. Preat's and R.F. Stocker's lab website.

Co-director in the theater group "les apostrophes" in 2006

RESEARCH PRODUCTS

Open source Software

- (2011-2013) CeTrAn 1.4 to 4.0, developed on Github (https://github.com/jcolomb/CeTrAn). Used for more than three research papers.
- (2016) Viewer data concatenator (shiny app).
- (2013-2016) Collaborating on Rfigshare and Rflybase (https://github.com/ropensci/rfigshare).

Peer review publications

Five most important publications:

- (2016). **Julien Colomb** and Björn Brembs.

 " PKC in motorneurons underlies self-learning, a form of motor learning in Drosophila" PeerJ (e1971).

 cited 3 times
- (2014). **Julien Colomb** and Björn Brembs. "Sub-strains of Drosophila Canton-S differ markedly in their locomotor behavior". F1000RESEARCH (3:176). cited 15 times
- (2009). **Julien Colomb**, Laure Kaiser, Marie-Ange Chabaud, Thomas Preat. "Parametric and genetic analysis of Drosophila appetitive long-term memory and sugar motivation" Genes Brain and Behaviour (8 (4): 407-415). cited 52 times
- (2007). **Julien Colomb**, Nicola Grillenzoni, Ariane Ramaekers, and Reinhard F. Stocker. "Architecture of the primary taste center of *Drosophila melanogaster* larvae". J. comp. neurol. (502: 834-847). cited 72 times
- (2007). **Julien Colomb**, Nicola Grillenzoni, Reinhard F. Stocker, and Ariane Ramaekers. "Complex behavioural changes after odour exposure in *Drosophila* larva". Anim. Behav. (73 (4): 579-85). cited 13 times

Other Publications

• (In revision). Christine Damrau, Naoko Toshima, Teiichi Tanimura, Björn Brembs Julien Colomb.

- "Octopamine and Tyramine contribute separately to the counter-regulatory response to sugar deficit in Drosophila." Frontiers
- (2014). Ezequiel Mendoza, **Julien Colomb**, Jürgen Rybak, Hans-Joachim Pflüger, Troy Zars, Constance Scharff, and Björn Brembs.
 - "Drosophila FoxP mutants are deficient in operant self-learning". Plos One (9(6): e100648).
- (2012). **Julien Colomb**, Lutz Reiter, Jedrzej Blaszkiewicz, Jan Wessnitzer and Björn Brembs.
 - "Open Source Tracking and Analysis of Adult *Drosophila* Locomotion in Buridan's Paradigm with and without Visual Targets." Plos One (7(8): e42247).
- (2010). **Julien Colomb**, Björn Brembs "biology of psychology: "simple conditioning"" Communicative and Integrative Biology (3 (2): 142-145).
- \bullet (2008). Julien Colomb
 - "Discriminative learning, learning generalization and masking tests as three strategies to assess olfactory discrimination." Animal Behaviour: New Research 185-192
- (2007). **Julien Colomb***, Rüdiger Bader*, Bettina Pankratz, Anne Schröck, Reinhard F. Stocker, and Michael J. Pankratz.
 - "Genetic dissection of a neural circuit underlying feeding behavior in Drosophila: distinct morphology of single hugin expressing neurons". J. comp. neurol. (502: 848-856).
 - * the two authors participated equally to this work.
- (2007). **Julien Colomb**, Reinhard F. Stocker "Combined rather than separate pathway for hedonic and sensory aspects of taste in *Drosophila* larvae." FLY (1 (4): 232-234).

Meeting presentations (4 most representative)

- 2016 Faster and more reproducible science: Open Science. ORAL PRESENTATION at the neurofly meeting, Creta, Greece.
- 2008 New insight into appetitive Long term memory in *Drosophila*. POSTER PRESENTATION at the FENS Forum, Geneva, Switzerland.
- 2006 Sub-regions in the primary taste center of *Drosophila* larvae. ORAL PRESENTATION at the 11th European Drosophila neurobiology Conference, Leuven, Belgium

 Learning by odor exposure in agar plate. ORAL PRESENTATION at the behavioural neurobiology of *Drosophila* larvae meeting, Würzburg, Germany.
- 2002 Functional studies of the chemosensory system of the Drosophila larva using a new tool: the GAL4 / UAS-shi ts system. ORAL PRESENTATION at the Swiss Drosophila meeting, Basel, Switzerland.